About a month back, I covered a study
that described an exciting relationship
between the molecule NAD and Alzheimer's
disease. Now, I won't retell the story
here, but it eventually turned into a
fascinating relationship between
ketosis, elevated ketones, and
Alzheimer's disease, where I pointed out
two clinical trials that indicate a link
between ketones and improving brain
function. But I couldn't go much into it
as much as I with as much depth as I
wanted. So, I promised this. Honestly,
there's more that I could say on the
topic, and I plan on revisiting this in
the future with a special emphasis on
this ketosis angle. So, here we are to
look at not one or two studies, but 13
studies, all in humans, that get into
the benefits of ketones and cognitive
health. What really shook me was the
biggest study on the topic found no
benefit. And yet there may be a very
good reason for that result that may not
preclude a conclusion for elevated blood
ketones causing improved cognitive
function. Let me show you what I mean as
well as assess two different ways of
raising ketones and how they both stack
against cognitive decline. It actually
all starts with this image. This is a
wicked wickedly cool image called a
tractogram. We're looking at two things
here. So one those millions of fine
fibers creating the mesh within the
brain outline are the connections
between the brain cells called neurons.
The second and the more relevant to use
is that this is a measure of ketone
uptake into the cells before and after a
person is on a ketogenic state. So a
ketosis production state. The more
green, the fewer ketones are taken up
and the more yellow, orange, and red,
the greater the ketone uptake by these
cells. Apart from being a fantastic
representation image of this study, it
speaks to the key proposed benefits of
elevated ketones in the blood. Ketones,
I suppose I should have explained that
earlier, are like essentially pre-
metabolized fat molecules produced by
your liver. And they can be used by your
brain cells like your neurons to
generate cellular energy via their
mitochondria, obligatory powerhouse of
the cell.
Now, the issue is with many brain
disorders that there's a shift away from
this primary nutrient. The brain uses
glucose, blood sugar. At least that's
what's proposed here. In addition, even
when glucose is present, the brain will
use ketones in a concentration dependent
manner, which means that if glucose is
held stable, but you raise your ketones,
the brain will preferentially utilize
ketones. So the main point that I'm
trying to get across here is that when
ketones are low, like in a non-
ketogenic state, the brain relies
heavily on glucose. And when the brain
reduces its utilization of glucose due
to disease, brain disorders worsen as
there's no backup energy substrate,
ketones. And as we saw in that image,
when a person is put into a position
where their body produces ketones, their
brain readily takes up those ketones.
And to be clear, there's other ways that
ketones are proposed to benefit the
brain, but the metabolic aspect is a
major one. But as I mentioned, there's a
serious disagreement in the literature
because larger studies disagree with
what I've shown in the past indicating
this unique benefit of ketones or at
least hinting strongly in that
direction. So, I originally showed these
two clinical trials which both show that
increasing ketones by supplementation
improved Alzheimer's disease, better
cognitive function. However, a larger
study on the back of these two studies
by one of the very same research groups
now indicates no effect. Although the
study ran for longer and had more
participants, as we can see here, if the
lines go up, that's improved cognitive
function. If the lines go down, that's
worse. And the dotted line is the
placebo group, those not consuming a
ketosis promoting supplement like
mediumchain triglycerides. And the black
line is the group consuming the ketosis
promoting MCTs and that's mediumchain
triglycerides. Again, since there's no
divergence between the lines over the 26
weeks, there's no effect detected and we
likely wouldn't detect an effect. Of
course, this spits in the face of the
other studies like this one where the
same type of intervention is used as in
MCT in red and placebo in blue. Again,
the higher the lines, the better
cognitive function. Notice how the
placebo experiences a loss in cognitive
function, yet the ketosis promoting
group maintain their cognitive function.
You may be wondering why the lines come
back together at the end. That's because
both groups stop their intervention,
meaning that the intervention itself is
the cause of this distinction, which is
good evidence. Now, while there are many
more studies that indicate an elevated
ketosis does improve cognitive function,
we should admit that some of these
studies are poorly controlled. For
example, this study has no control group
and some studies are quite short,
running only a month or so, or having
only a handful of participants or the
fact that many of the studies are
industry funded or affiliated. Still,
even slightly larger studies, including
proper controls, less conflicted studies
indicate there is a benefit here to be
had. So, why the discrepancy and what to
believe? Now, I'm going to get into
that, plus comparing the natural ways of
raising ketones versus the supplemented
ways. But before we do that and get into
the specifics, I'm covering more on the
mechanisms of ketones, if APOE4
Alzheimer's status makes a difference,
and even some work on pairing of two
other molecules with ketones and the
effect against cognitive decline. All of
that in video, podcast, and article form
are available as a physionic insider.
And you get all of these additional
benefits as well. If you're interested,
check out the link in the description
for the Physionic Insiders. I'd love to
have you aboard. Okay, I'm not going to
be the purveyor of absolute truth here,
but my educated speculation, which is
also mentioned by the researchers of
this study indicating failure, is that
participants did not reach a blood
ketone threshold. What am I talking
about? I'm talking about a minimum blood
ketone threshold to reach before
benefits set in. The study showed that
people reached 0.27 27 mill mole ketone
levels. This is quite low. In fact, most
studies that indicate benefit reach
double that blood level if not higher.
So, it is completely feasible that this
study fail to indicate an effect simply
because the intervention didn't deliver
enough of the nutrient of interest,
ketones. There are of course other
possibilities like participants dropping
out or the effect only being present at
certain early stages of Alzheimer's and
cognitive decline or something entirely
different. Still, I think that this
failed minimum threshold is a probable
cause and requires a search warrant for
future investigation. So, the bottom
line is this. Boosting ketones has
inconsistent evidence indicating brain
benefit, but almost all of the evidence
suggests a protective effect. Now, allow
me to take a step back because there's
three more quick things to cover before
we finish this off. First, many studies
look at raising ketones in the blood via
supplementation, those mediumchain
triglycerides. Unfortunately, we can't
technically attribute these benefits to
ketosis, even if that is what is assumed
considering the research on the
mechanisms. It's not like we're knocking
out the ketone production and seeing if
that eliminates the effects here. I
suppose in the big picture it probably
doesn't matter but it does matter in how
we discuss this topic. The assumption is
that the main driver is through ketone
production something that I may dive
into with specific mechanistic
literature in the future. And second, do
we have similar evidence with something
like ketogenic diets, other forms of
raising ketones? The answer is yes.
There are some studies looking at very
low carbohydrate diets and they all
point the same direction benefit.
However, there isn't as much evidence or
as quality evidence as for mediumchain
triglycerides. Still, since we now have
two intersection interventions, MCTs and
ketogenic diets, it does strengthen the
interpret interpretation that these
effects are ketone related. This also
means that supplementation is likely
unnecessary. So if I wanted to implement
this, it would depend on if I wanted to
turn my diet to be ketone generation, so
i.e. long-term very low carbohydrate
diet, or if I wanted to maintain my
higher carbohydrate diet, but add MCTs.
Both would likely work as the evidence
suggests. Okay, that brings us to a
third point that's especially true here.
MCTs can have some side effects like
gastrointestinal issues. So that may
factor into the equation for you too. Or
certain ketogenic diets can raise
cardiovascular risk factors as we
currently understand the literature. So
if you went that route, focusing on
unsaturated fats may be prudent. But
listen, all of this started when I was
looking at a molecule called NAD and the
relationship it has to ketosis and brain
function. If you're interested in
learning more, then check out my
analysis right here. Or if you prefer to
learn more about the potential benefits
of ketones in general, then check this
out right here. I hope this was
informative. Thanks for hanging out with
me and I'll catch you in the next one.
See you.